[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
this quarter we're going to learn about
field Theory classical field
[Applause]
Theory
Fields such as the electromagnetic field
gravitational
field other fields in
nature which I won't name right
now propagate which means they change
according to rules which give them a
wavelike character moving through
space and one of the fundamental
principles of field
theory in fact more
broadly nature in general
is the principle of
Relativity the principle special the
principle of special relativity in this
particular
case the principle of special relativity
well let's just call it the principle of
Relativity goes way back there was not
an invention of
Einstein's I'm not absolutely sure when
it was first announced or articulated in
the form which I'll spell it out
I don't know whether it was Galileo or
Newton or those who came after them but
those early Pioneers certainly had the
right
idea it begins with the idea of an
inertial reference frame now an inertial
reference frame this is's a something a
bit tautological about an inertial
reference frame Newton's equations fals
ma are satisfied in an inertial
reference frame what is an inertial
reference frame it's a frame of
reference in which Newton's equations
are
satisfied I'm not going to explain any
further what an inertial reference frame
is except to say that the idea of an
inertial reference frame is by no means
unique a reference frame first of all
what does a reference frame entail a a
reference frame first of all entails a
set of coordinate axes in ordinary
space x y and z
and you know how to think about those
but it also entails the idea that the
coordinate system may be
moving or not moving relative to whom
relative to whomever we sitting here or
you sitting here in this uh classroom
here Define a frame of
reference we can pick the vertical
direction to be the z-axis the
horizontal Direction along my arms here
to be the x-axis X plus that way x x is
minus in that direction and which one
have I left out I've left out uh the Y
AIS which points toward you from
me so there are some coordinate axes for
Space X Y and Z and in add in addition
to specify a frame of reference one also
imagines that this
entire coordinate system is is moving in
some way relative to you sitting there
presumably with a uniform velocity in a
definite
direction if your frame of reference is
an inertial frame of reference in other
words if when you throw balls around or
juggle or do whatever you're supposed to
do in an inertial frame of reference if
you find yourself in an inertial frame
of reference then every other frame of
reference that's moving with uniform
velocity
relative to you now remember what
uniform velocity means it doesn't just
mean with uniform speed it means with
uniform speed in an unchanging
Direction such a frame of reference is
also inertial if it's
accelerated uh if it starts standing
still and then suddenly picks up some
speed then it's not an inertial frame of
reference all inertial frames of
reference according to Newton and and
also I think also Galileo Galileo was
often credited with the idea but I never
read enough of Galileo to know whether
he actually had it or not
uh neither did I read enough of
Newton they both wrote in languages that
I don't
understand
um what was I saying oh
yes right according to both Newton and
anybody else who uh thought about it
very
hard the laws of physics are the same in
all inertial reference frames laws of
physics meaning fals ma the forces
between objects all the things that we
would normally call laws of nature or
laws of physics don't distinguish
between one frame of reference and
another if you want a kind of pictorial
example that I like to use a lot when
I'm explaining this
uh to um uh to children or to grown-ups
I like to think about the laws of
juggling there are very definite
procedures that you train your body to
do uh in order to be able to juggle
balls
correctly now you can imagine yourself
being in a railroad car moving with
perfectly uniform velocity down the
x-axis and trying to juggle do you have
to compensate for the fact that the
train is moving in particular when you
throw a ball up into the air do you have
to reach over to the right to compensate
for the fact that the train is moving to
the left my left your right the answer
is no you don't the laws of juggling are
the same in every reference frame in
every inertial reference frame whatever
you do in one reference frame you do
exactly the same thing and you'll
succeed or fail depending on whether
you're a good juggler or not but it will
not depend on whether you're moving with
uniform velocity so the laws of juggling
are the same in every inertial reference
frame the laws of mechanics are the same
in every inertial reference frame the
laws Newtonian laws of gravity are the
same in every inertial frame according
to
Newton what about the laws of electrical
phenomena
well there there was a
Clash The Clash had to do with Maxwell's
equations Maxwell's equations were the
field equations the field theory that
governed the electromagnetic field and
the way that it propagated and sent
waves electromagnetic waves that we
ordinarily call light or radio waves or
so forth and the fundamental dilemma as
you all know I'm sure you all know uh
the fundamental dilemma was both
according to to well here was the
Dilemma Maxwell's equations said light
moves with a certain
velocity if you take the various
constants that appear in Maxwell's
equations and put them together in the
right way you get the velocity of waves
moving down an axis and that velocity
comes out to be a certain number out of
Maxwell's equations you have two
choices one is to believe that Maxwell's
equations are true laws of nature as
good as any other laws of nature in
which case the principle of Relativity
says they should be the same in every
reference
frame but if it follows from Maxwell's
equations that the speed of light
is 3 * 10 8 m/s which is about what it
is if it follows from Maxwell's
equations that light moves that fast and
if Maxwell's equations are laws of
physics fundamental laws of physics
and if the laws of physics are the same
in every reference frame then the speed
of light must be the same in every
reference frame but that was very hard
to swallow because if a light beam is
going down that axis and you chase it
and run along with it that let's say 3/4
of the speed of light then you ought to
see that light Ray moving much more
slowly than three * 108 m/s relative to
you on the other hand the light Ray
going in the other direction since
you're sort of running into it you
should see going even
faster
so all these possibilities could not
simultaneously be correct that the laws
of nature are the same in every
reference frame and that Maxwell's
equations are laws of physics in the
same sense that Newton's laws of physics
namely the same in every reference frame
something had to
give well the point was of course that
they were good laws of nature and that
they were the same in every reference
frame the thing that had to give is our
concepts of velocity space and time and
how we measure
velocity especially velocities were up
which are up near the speed of light now
I'm not going to spend the full amount
of time that I did previously on the
special theory of relativity that can be
found on lectures from how long ago or
they're on the internet I believe
relativity and electromagnetism I think
that was maybe about 3/4s ago I've lost
track yeah they're up there they're on
the net and uh they're the lectures on
relativity special relativity and
electromagnetic
Theory we're just going to cut through
it real fast we're going to cut through
the basic ideas of Relativity a little
more mathematically than I would do if I
were teaching it for the first time if I
teach it the first time I tend to teach
it the way uh
Einstein first conceived of it how do
you measure distances how do you measure
velocities how do how does the
propagation of light influen these
things instead I'm going to take a more
mathematical view of
it and think about the properties
of various kinds of um coordinate
Transformations coordinates now consist
not only of X Y and Z but also time T so
imagine every event in the
world is characterized by just like
every particle would be characterized by
a position X Y and Z every event taking
place in SpaceTime is characterized by
four coordinates x y z and
T let's suppress for the moment Y and
Z let's just forget forget them for the
moment and concentrate on x and t that
would be appropriate if we were mainly
interested in motion along one axis
let's focus on that motion along the x
axis let's Suppose there is no motion
along Y and Z then we can forget Y and Z
for the moment momentarily we come back
to them and think of motion along x and
t and the various reference frames that
might be moving along the
x-axis all right here's
here's time
vertically here's space
horizontally physicists always draw
space
horizontally and time vertically I found
out that mathematicians or at least um
certain computer scientist always draw
time going horizontally I didn't know
that and I got into an enormous argument
with a quantum computer scientist which
was ultimately resolved by the fact that
he had time going horizontally and I had
it going vertically
uh these are Traditions I guess
Traditions grow up around subjects but
time is north and X is East I
guess or at least time is upward yeah
think the mathematicians are thinking
independent yeah yeah that's what that
that that's the point that is the point
yes they're thinking of time as the
independent variable and everybody knows
that it's a law of nature that the
independent variable should be
horizontal
right all right now let's let's imagine
a moving Observer moving down the x-axis
with a velocity
V let's take his origin of spatial
coordinates his origin of spatial
coordinates at time T equals z is just
at the same let's assume that my I'm
I'll be the moving Observer I move down
the x-axis I am my own
origin there's nobody who is your origin
that seed is vacant over there so that
absence of uh of human over there is
the center of the x coordinates in your
frame I'm the X Prime coordinates and of
course I being very egocentric will take
my X my x uh origin to be where I am
there I do I move down the x- axis we
pass each other our Origins pass each
other at T equals z
so that means at T equals z your axis
and my Axis are the same or your origin
and my origin is the same but then as I
move down the x axis my coord my
coordinate Center moves to the right it
moves to the right that's supposed to be
a straight line it's as as good as I can
do under the circumstances that's a
straight line and it's moving with
velocity V which means it's X Prime
equals sorry means xal VT
but it's also that's the way you
describe it in terms of your
coordinates my Center you describe by
saying x equals VT how do I describe
it I just say x Prime my coordinate X
Prime is
zero X Prime equal 0 is the same as xal
VT all right what's the relationship
between X Prime and x and t
well it's easy to work out if you
believe this
picture the X Prime
coordinate is the distance from my
origin the x coordinate is the distance
from your
origin so one of these is X the other is
X Prime the upper one here is X Prime
the lower one here is X and the
relationship between them is that they
differ by an amount VT
in particular X is equal to X Prime
minus VT or X Prime is equal to x +
VT do I have it wrong yes I do X Prime
is x minus VT and X is X prime plus VT
yeah I think I have that that's correct
now all right what about time
itself well according to Newton and
according to Galileo and according to
everybody who came afterward up until
Einstein time is just time is just time
is just time there was no notion that
time might be different in different
reference
frames Newton had the idea of a
universal time sort of God's time God up
on his Cloud ticking off with his with
his super accurate watch and that time
was Universal for everybody no matter
how they were moving
and so everybody would agree on what on
the time of Any Given event in this map
of space and time here and so the other
equation that went with this is that t
Prime is equal to
T let's forget the top equation here
let's just forget
it one might say that this was the
Newtonian or the Galilean transformation
properties between X and T your
coordinates and the coordinates that I
ascribe to a point in
SpaceTime now let's examine a light Ray
moving down the plus X
AIS if it starts at the origin here then
it moves along a trajectory which is xal
CT C being the speed of light now
shortly I'm going to set c equal to 1
we're going to work in units in which C
is equal to 1 but not quite
yet
incidentally once you understand a bit
of
Relativity working in coordinates in
which C is not equal to one is about as
stupid as using different units for X
and Y uh if we used yards for x and feet
for y then we would have all kinds of
funny factors in our equations which
would be conversion factors from X with
which is measured in feet to Y which is
measured in um uh
yards those scale has its uses H log
scale has its uses well I don't know log
scale I don't think you do log scale
well like compound interest yeah I'm not
sure what getting it but okay I'm just
saying it is quite often in Practical
circumstances that one uses different
scales yeah sometimes you might there
might be a good reason I mean um
it wouldn't be totally unreasonable for
a sailor to use different units for
horizontal Direction and vertical
Direction h i mean he's used to moving
around horizontally he might use what
miles uh miles versus fathoms or
something nautical miles versus fathoms
yeah I'm not sure if this question is
relevant
if but um when you talk about a uh um
frame of reference you need to specify a
period of time because obviously go back
15 billion years there is no yeah yeah
we're ignoring now the fact that the
Universe began at some time and uh we're
imagining now as Newton did and as the
early Einstein did that the Universe has
just been here forever and ever and ever
unchanging totally static and space and
time have properties which don't change
with time now of course that's incorrect
Cor in the real world and at some point
we will take up the subject of cosmology
and find that's not right but as long as
we're interested in time intervals which
are not I I suspect this is what you're
getting at as long as we're interested
in time intervals which are not too long
in particular time intervals over which
the universe doesn't expand very much
and so forth we can mainly say the
properties of space don't change over a
period of time and so everything just uh
stays the same as always was is that
what you're asking well it it seems that
that this assumption if it is made it
leads to what you're describing so so
the question is would that eventually
lead to some uh the point is it doesn't
lead it doesn't lead to what I'm
describing okay where there's this this
room for different uh formulas here this
is a Formula which was based on an
assumption the Assumption being that
time is universal
that's what Einstein found was wrong
basically what he found is that when
you're in a moving frame of reference
two different observers will not agree
about what time a particular event takes
place this is the culprit here this one
and some modifications to this one but
in any case to see what's wrong let's go
to Maxwell's equations Maxwell's
equations say that light always moves
with this velocity
C being some numbers in
m/s okay 3 * 10 8
m/s we will later as I said say C equals
1 Let's imagine a light beam moving down
the x-axis let's describe how X Prime
sees it in other words you see the light
move this way to the right how do I See
the Light well let's see what I see
let's just work it out X Prime will be X
which is CT for that light Ray minus
VT which is the same as C minus
VT all this says is that I See the Light
moving with a diminished velocity a
velocity C minus V why is that because
I'm moving along with the light so
naturally I see it move slowly but slow
compared to what you see
it what about the light going in the
other direction supposing it was a light
beam going in the other direction then
how would you describe it you would
describe it as x = minus
CT and if I do exactly the same thing I
will find that X Prime is equal to X
that's minus
CT minus VT which is the same
as minus C + V *
T so what this says is that I will see
the light move moving also in the
negative Direction that's the minus sign
but I'll see it moving with an enhanced
velocity C+
V If This Were the right story and if
these were the right transformation laws
for space and time then it could not be
the case that Maxwell's equations are
laws of physics or laws of nature in the
sense that they were true in every
reference frame they would have to be
corrected did in moving frames just like
the juggler who had to reach to the
right who didn't actually but who
thought he had to reach to the right to
collect the ball when train is
moving the physicist interested in light
beams would have to correct things for
the motion of his reference frame now
it's an experimental fact that this is
not the case that you don't have to
correct for motion was the famous
Michaelson moley
experiment Einstein he just reject Ed uh
he just felt this can't be right
Maxwell's equations were much too
beautiful to be relegated to the
approximate or to the contingent on
which reference
frame and so he set about to find a
framework in which the speed of light
would be the same in every reference
frame and he basically focused on these
equations and after various very very
beautiful gunkan experiments thought
experiments about light and about
measuring and so forth he came to a set
of
formulas
uh called the Lorent
Transformations I'm going to explain the
Loren
Transformations um in a more
mathematical way not fancy mathematics
but just
uh get we want to get right to the heart
of it and not spend uh 3 weeks doing it
the best way is to set up a math
mathematical problem but before I do let
me set up a different mathematical
problem uh which
is for most of you you've seen me do
this before but nonetheless let's go
through it again the problem of rotation
of coordinates we're going to do this
quickly let's just take spatial
coordinates now for the moment
two-dimensional spatial coordinates
let's forget x and t and just
concentrate on X and Y two coordinates
in space instead of events in space time
concentrate on a point in space a point
in space has
coordinates and we can determine those
coordinates the X and Y coordinates just
by dropping perpendiculars to the x-axis
and the Y AIS and we would describe this
point as the point at position let's
just call it
XY now there's nothing sacred about
horizontal and vert
vertical so somebody else might come
along some crazy
mathematician a really nutty one who
wants to use coordinates which are at an
angle relative to the
vertical maybe a couple of beers and you
don't know the difference between uh
vertical and uh uh what what what we
should give this direction a name
oblique yeah all right the oblique
Observer the blue Observer can blue be
seen everybody can see blue okay good uh
the blue Observer also characterizes
points by coordinates which he calls X
Prime and Y
Prime the X Prime and the Y Prime
coordinates are found by dropping
perpendiculars to the X Prime and the Y
Prime axis so here's X Prime here's y
Prime and given a point
XY there's a rule it must be a rule if
you know the value of X and Y you should
be able to deduce the value of x Prime
and Y Prime if you know the angle
between the two coordinates between the
x coordinate and the X Prime coordinate
and the formula is simple we we've used
it this in these classes many times I'll
just remind you what it is it's X Prime
is equal
to x * cosine of the angle between the
two frames between the two coordinate
systems minus y * s of the
angle and y Prime is equal
to minus uh plus I think X sin of
theta plus y cosine Theta
I just want to remind you about a little
bit of
trigonometry all of
trigonometry is
encoded in two very simple
formulas I've used them the signs on
these signs are you're right let's hold
on X X Prime is bigger than x for small
Theta say the science here wrong yeah so
it's it's
XE is bigger than x is
it
yeah if you rotate it to the next so
that um Y is y Prime is zero it's
further
out X
Prime do I have it backward
yeah I don't know I'm not sure I'm not
convinced no I'm not either
um so let's see just make sure the link
X Prime is the little perpendicular
there on no y Prime is a little that's y
Prime yeah so y Prime is this is y Prime
here right right that's y Prime here x
Prime is bigger than x so there has to
be a plus sign on the second ter how do
you know X Prime is bigger than x let's
see um yeah X Prime is bigger than x
yeah X Prime is bigger than x looks like
that's probably right probably sign but
then this one must be negative yeah
okay there's an easy way to uh correct
for it another way to correct for it
just call this angle minus Theta that
would also do the trick because cosine
of minus Theta is the same as cosine of
theta and S changes sign when you change
Theta to minus Theta so if instead of
calling this angle Theta I called it
minus Theta then my previous formulas
would be
right it's true true but uh it's an
excuse all right what do we know about s
and cosine it's important to understand
s and cosign everything you ever learned
about trigonometry can be codified in
two very simple
formulas if you know about complex
numbers the two very simple formulas are
that
cine of theta is e to the I theta plus
eus I Theta / 2 and S of theta is e to
the I Theta
minus E to Theus I Theta over 2
I those two formulas contain everything
about trigonometry you don't have to
know any other formulas other than these
for example I will assign you the
homework problem of using these two
formulas to find cosine of the sum of
two angles but the way you would do it
is just write the sum of two angles in
here and then
reexpress the exponentials in terms of
cosine and S that's easy to do e to the
I
Theta is equal to cosine of
theta plus I sin
Theta and E to Theus I Theta is cosine
of thetus I sin Theta so work through
these formulas get familiar with them
they're extremely useful formulas once
you know them you will never have to
remember any trigonometric formulas
again right the other thing to know is
that e to the I Theta * e to minus I
Theta is 1 right e to the anything time
e to the minus the same thing is one
those things car characterize all
trigonometric formulas in
particular as was EXP explained to me by
Michael a number of times if we multiply
e to the I Theta * eus I Theta we will
get one on this side but on this side we
will get cine squar of theta plus sin
squ of theta not minus sin squ but plus
sin squ cosine squar and then IUS i^ s
sin squ that gives us cosine s + sin s
cosine s Theta + sin sare
th so that's equivalent to the fact that
e to the I thet * eus I Theta is
1 all right now the most important
fact that again follows from the simple
trigonometry is that when you make the
change of
coordinates from XY to X Prime y Prime
something is left
unchanged namely the distance from the
origin to the point
XY that's
something which is you know you you
count the number of the molecules along
the Blackboard from here to here and
that doesn't change when I change
coordinates so the distance from the
origin to the point
XY has to be the same independent of
which coordinate axes we use well let's
take the square of that distance the
square of that distance we know what it
is it's X let's call it s
squ I'm not sure why I use S but s for
distance s s for distance s for space I
think it must be for space that I'm
using it for the space for the spatial
distance from the origin to the point XY
we know what that is it's Pythagoras's
Theorem x^2 +
y^2 but as I said there's nothing
special about the XY axis we also ought
to be able to calculate it as X s + y
Prime
s well it's not too hard to work out
that X Prime s + y Prime 2 is x^2 +
y^2 it's easy to use do uh X Prime 2 + y
Prime s will have x^2 cine 2 Theta it
will also have x^2 sin 2 Theta when you
add them you'll get x s + y sare you
know you know the the
rigal uh so it follows from cine 2 + sin
2 = 1 that X Prime 2 + y Prime s equals
also equal is equal to x^2 + y^2 work
that out make sure that you have this
under control that you understand why
from the trigonometry not from the the
basic physics of it or the basic
geometry of it is
clear make sure that you understand that
you can see that from the
trigonometry okay
one last thing about SS and
cosiness if I plot on the
Blackboard for every angle if I plot s
or cosign along the horizontal
axis supposing I plot cosine of theta
along the horizontal axis and S of theta
along the vertical
axis then if I plot all Poss ible
angles they will correspond to a bunch
of points that lie on a unit circle why
on a unit circle because sin s + cosine
squ =
so one might
call the properties of s and cosine the
properties of circular functions
circular in that they're convenient for
rotating they're convenient for
describing unit circles point points on
unit circles are described in terms of
coordinates which are cosiness and signs
of angles and so forth it's natural to
call them circular
functions these are these are not the
functions that come in to the
transformation the new transformation
properties first of all these are
wrong I'm not I don't want to use x
Let's
uh x a bar yeah yeah no just
wrong Newton had it wrong Newton or
Galileo or whoever it was postulate who
postulated it Einstein modified it now
we're going to have to make sure that
Einstein's
modification doesn't change things in
situations where Newton new where
Newton's equations were good
approximations
the situations where Einstein's model
ifications are important is when we're
talking about frames of reference moving
very rapidly up near the speed of light
before the 20th century nobody or
nothing had ever moved faster than than
100 miles an hour probably well of
course some things did light did but for
all practical purposes light didn't
travel at all it just when you turned on
the switch light just went on uh so
light didn't travel
nothing in anybody's experience direct
experience traveled faster than 100 or
200 M an hour and well I should say
nothing traveled faster than 100 miles
an hour and then live to tell about
it so all of experience was about very
slow velocities on the scale of the
speed of light on the scale of such
velocities Newton's formulas must be
correct they work they're they're very
useful they work uh Newton got away with
it so they must be uh good
approximations it had better be that
whatever Einstein did to the equations
in particular to these two equations
here had better reduced to Newton's
equations in the appropriate limit okay
let's come back now to light light
according to the Newton formulas doesn't
always move with a speed of
light but uh let's uh let's try to
figure out what it would mean of a
better formula of a replacement for this
that light always moves with the speed
of
light first of all let's set the speed
of light equal to one that's a choice of
units in particular it's a choice
of the relation between space units and
time units if we work
in
um light years for for distance and
years for time then light moves one
light year per year the speed of light
is one if we use seconds and light
seconds it's also one Whatever Whatever
scale we use for space if we use for
time the time that it takes light to go
that distance one unit of space if we
use that for time units then the speed
of light is equal to one now from the
ordinary point of view of very slowly
moving things those are odd units but if
we were electrons with neutrinos and
whizzing around like photons they would
be the natural units for us uh speed of
light equals 1 so let's set the speed of
light equal to one as I said it's just a
choice of units and then a light Ray
moving to the right just moves along a
trajectory xal
T C is just equal to one a light Ray
moving to the left is xal minus
t how can we take both both of these
equations and put them together sorry x
= minus
t can I write a single equation which if
it's satisfied is a light Ray either
moving to the left or to the right yes
here's an equation X2 = T ^2 it has two
solutions x = t and x = minus t the two
square roots well X2 = t^2 is equivalent
to either x = t or or x = minus t in
other words this equation here is a
necessary and
sufficient condition for describing the
motion of a light Ray either to the
right or to the
left supposing we found a replacement
for this equation which had the
following interesting
property that whenever oh let's let's
write it this way x^2 minus t^2 = 0 this
is even better for our purposes x^2 - t
^2 =
0 that's the necessary and sufficient
condition to describe the motion of a
light
Ray supposing we found a new set of
rules a new set of transformation
properties
which which um had the
property that if x^2 - T ^2 is equal to
0 then we would find that X Prime 2 - t
Prime 2 is equal to
zero in other words supposing this
implied
this and vice
versa then it would follow that what the
unprimed Observer you in your seats see
as a light Ray the primed Observer me
moving along also as a light Ray both of
us agreeing that light rays move with
unit
velocity now this doesn't work for
Newton's formula here it just doesn't
work if x is equal to T it does not
follow that X Prime is equal to T Prime
in fact it says something quite
different okay so the form of these
equations must be
wrong let's look for some better
equations now at this point oh let's in
fact let's even be a little bit more
ambitious it turns out being a little
bit more ambitious actually simplifies
things let's not only say that when x^2
- t^2 is equal to 0 then X Prime s minus
t Prime 2 is equal to0 let's say
something even
Bolder let's say the relation between XT
and X Prime T Prime is such that x^2 -
t^2
is equal to X Prime 2 - t Prime
2 in other words pick any X and any T
and calculate x^2 - t
^2 then take the same point except
reckoned in the primed coordinates in
other words we take a certain event a
light bulb goes off
someplace you say that corresponds to x
and t
I say it corresponds to X Prime and T
Prime but let's require just to try it
out see if we can do it let's look for
Transformations so that x^2 - t ^2 will
always be equal to X Prime 2 - t Prime 2
that would be enough to ensure that
everybody will agree about the speed of
light
why if x^2 - t ^2 = X Prime minus t
Prime squ for all x and t and so forth
then when x^2 - t ^2 = 0 x Prime - t
Prime 2 would be 0 and then if this is a
light Ray so is this a light Ray
everybody get the
logic okay good so let's assume now that
let's ask can we find Transformations
which have this particular property now
it's not so
different from looking for
transformations
which
preserve x^2 + y^2 = x Prime 2 + y Prime
s it's just a little minus sign other
than a minus sign here x² minus t^2 the
look of these two is very
similar and the
mathematics is quite
similar here are the
Transformations which preserve X2 Plus
plus
y^2 what are the Transformations which
preserve x^2 minus
t^2 well they are the lorence
Transformations they are the fundamental
transformations of the special theory of
relativity they're not this but they're
closely related or perhaps one should
say closely analogous to these equations
here but we have to substitute for
circular trigonometry hyperbolic
trigonometry so let's go go back and
remember a little bit about hyperbolic
functions instead of circular
functions well I didn't want to erase
that all right these are the basic rules
governing circular functions cosine
Theta is equal to this sin Theta is
equal to this
and the uh
e to the I Theta in terms of cosine and
S all right let's see if we have a now
we do have a blank Blackboard here let
me write whoops what did I do here I
erased something I didn't mean to erase
here it is
okay incidentally does everybody see how
I got this side from this
side just add and subtract the equations
appropriately and uh you isolate e to
the I Theta and e to the minus I Theta
that's Elementary exercise all right
hyperbolic functions what are hyperbolic
functions right those are functions of
the
form hyperbolic
cosine
K hyperbolic cosine first first of all
the angle Theta is replaced by a
variable called Omega which I will call
Omega Omega is called a hyperbolic angle
it doesn't go from 0 to 2 pi and then
wind around on a circle it goes from
minus infinity to
Infinity goes from minus infinity to
Infinity so it's a variable that just
extends over the entire real
axis but it's defined in a manner fairly
similar to cosine and S C Omega is by
definition you're not allowed to ask why
this is definition e to the
Omega plus e to Theus Omega /
2 all we do is substitute for Theta or
for Omega Theta I Theta substitute Omega
and that gives you hyperbolic
functions likewise or similar Sly
there's the hyperbolic
sign and that's given by e to the Omega
minus E Theus Omega /
2 essentially you throw away all I's out
of that formula out of the top
formulas just throw away all All
Eyes the equations on the right hand
side
become e to the
Omega equals hyper bolic C Omega plus
cinch
Omega and e to the minus Omega equals
cos
Omega minus cinch
Omega I think that's right is it
right
Kos minus
cinch it is yeah it is
right okay now what about the analog of
cosine 2 + sin^2 = 1 that simply came by
multiplying this one by this one so
let's do the same
operation multiplying e to the Omega by
E by e to the minus Omega gives
one and now that gives k^ squar minus
cing squ you see we're getting a minus
what we want we want that minus the
minus is important we want
the well somewhere is under here was a
formula with a minus
sign yeah we want to get that minus into
play
here that's cos Omega
squar no not Co but k^ s Omega minus
sinin squ
Omega so it's very similar every
everything you want to know about
hyperbolic trigonometry and the theory
of these functions is called hyperbolic
trigonometry everything you ever want to
know is codified in these simple
formulas these and these and they're
more or less definitions but they're
rather useful definitions now yeah go
ahead it mentioning
that Conant a circle yeah
and Conant not only is it worth
mentioning I was just about to mention
it sorry X2 - y^2 is what x - y constant
is a hyperbola hyperbola yeah right
exactly so if I were to play the same
game that I did here namely plot on the
horizontal and vertical axis the values
not of cosine of theta and S of
theta but cine cosine k of Omega and
cinch
Omega that's in other words on the x
axis now we're going to
plot cos Omega and on the Y AIS
cinch
Omega then this is a hyperbola not a
circle but a
hyperbola and it's a
hyperbola with Asm tootes that are at
45° you can
see let me show you
why why the asmp tootes are at
45° when Omega is very
large when Omega is very large then e to
the minus Omega is very small right when
Omega is very large e to Theus Omega is
very small and that means both Kos and
cinch are both essentially equal to e to
the plus
Omega in other words when Omega gets
very big Kos and cinch become equal to
each other and that's this line here
Kash equals cinch along this line here
so when Omega gets very large the curve
ASM toes to uh to a curve which is at
45° it's not hard to see that in the
other direction when Omega is very
negative that uh that it ASM tootes to
the other ASM totic line
here so that's why it's called
hyperbolic geometry it um the hyperbolic
angle the hyperbolic angles the kosas
the cinches play the same role relative
to
hyperbolas as signs and cosiness do to
circles
any
questions so let's see no question K
Omega equals zero how how would you plot
that
hyperb oh cos squ - sin s equal 0 no
that's no no cos squ - sin square equals
1 in the same sense that sin square plus
cosine Square it never equals
zero I think I think you wanted to ask a
different question
I oh well since Omega equals 0 is the
horizontal
axis cos Omega equals 0 is the vertical
axis right okay well x intercept yeah
it's it's the vertex yeah I was just
thinking here's one point on the graph
yeah the x intercept there is
one yeah because K Kos of Z is
one to see that just plug one or zero in
here 1 + 1 iD two is
1 at least it was
yesterday yeah still
is okay so now we we we're sort of
starting to cook a little bit we're
starting to see something that has that
nice minus sign in it but what's it got
to do with x and t and X Prime and T T
Prime we're now set up to make let's
call it a
guess but it's a guess which is based on
the extreme
similarity between hyperbolas and
circles CES and cosiness and so forth
here's the guess I'm going to make and
then we'll check it we'll see if it does
the thing we want it to do
my formula instead of being this is
we're now going to have instead of X and
Y we're going to have x and
t time and X later on we'll put back Y
and Z we're going to have to put back Y
and Z but they're very easy okay so
let's start with X Prime X Prime is the
coordinate given to a point of space
time by the moving Observer namely
me and I'm going to guess that it's some
combination of x and t not too different
but not the same as where is it X Prime
= x - VT I'm going to
try cos
Omega
X let's write X cos
minus t cinch
Omega sort of parallel with
this I could put a plus sign here but
you can go back and forth between the
plus and the minus by changing the sign
of Omega just as you did here so this
let's do it this way X cos Omega minus t
cinch
Omega and T
Prime going to look similar but without
the extra minus sign here this you know
the relation between SS cosiness and CES
and cines is one of just leaving out an
i you go from SS and cosiness to CES and
cinches by leaving out the
I well if you track it through carefully
you'll find that this minus sign was
really an i
squared it's it's not going to matter
much I will just tell you it was really
came from some I squared and if you
leave out I I squar just becomes 1 squar
there's no minus sign so here's the
guess for for the formula connecting X
Prime T Prime with x and t it equals
let's see x c
Omega minus no
minus plus T cos
Omega in this case there are two minus
signs in this case there was only one
minus sign okay okay but but let's check
what do we want to check we want to
check that X Prime
2us T Prime s is equal to x^2 -
t^2 you're ask you're probably asking
yourself what is this Omega what does it
have to do with moving reference
frames I'll tell you right now what
Omega is it's a standing for the
velocity between the frames we're going
to find the Rel relationship between
Omega and the relative velocity of the
reference frames in a
moment there has to be a parameter in
the Laurent these are the lence these
are the Lorent
Transformations connecting two frames of
reference in the Loren Transformations
is a parameter it's the velocity the
relative velocity that parameter has
been replaced by Omega it's a kind of
angle relating the two frames a
hyperbolic angle but we'll we'll come
back to that for the moment let's prove
that with this transformation law
here that X Prime 2us T Prime 2 is equal
to zero ah is equal to x^2 - t ^2 I'm
getting to that point in the evening
where I'm going to make mistakes all
right this is
easy you just work it out you use all
you have to use is that cosine 2us sin^2
is 1 you can work that out by yourself
but we can just see little pieces of it
here x Prime s will have x^2 cos 2 Omega
T Prime s will have x^2 sin s Omega if I
take the difference between them I'll
get a term with an x^2 * cos 2 - sin s
but cos s minus sin s is
1 all right so we'll find the term with
an X squ when we Square take the square
of the the difference between the
squares of this and this and likewise
we'll also find the t^2 the cross term
when you square X Prime you'll have XT
Kos cinch when you Square t Prime you'll
have XT Kos cinch When you subtract them
it'll cancel and it's easy to check it's
a basically oneliner to show that with
this transformation here x Prime 2 minus
t^ 2 is x^2 - t ^2 which is exactly what
we're looking for let me remind you why
we looking for it if we find a
transformation for which the left hand
side and the right hand side are
equal then if
X2 equals t^2 in other words if the
right hand side is zero the left hand
side will also be
zero but x² but xal T that's the same as
something moving with a speed of light
in the X frame of reference
if this being zero is equivalent to the
left hand side being zero it says that
in both frames of reference the light
rays move with the same
velocity okay so that's the basic that's
the basic tool that we're using
here x Prime 2 - t Prime 2 is equal to
x^2 -
t^2 all right that does
Follow by a couple of lines using cos^2
- sin^2 = 1 but what I want to do let's
take another couple of
minutes no let's take a break for five
minutes and then come back and connect
these variables Omega with the velocity
of the moving frame of
reference somebody asked me a question
about um The Ether
and what it was that people were
thinking somehow Einstein never got
trapped into this mode of
thinking
um what what were they thinking about
when they were thinking about The Ether
what exactly was the Michaelson Mor
experiment well I'll just spend a minute
or two uh uh mentioning
it certainly Maxwell
understood that his equations were not
consistent with
um with Newtonian relativity he
understood that but his image of what
was going on is that the propagation of
light was very similar to the
propagation of sound in a
material or water
waves propagating on
water and of course it is true that if
you move relative to the atmosphere or
move relative to the substance that
sound is propagating in you'll see sound
move with different velocities depending
on your motion if you're at rest in a
gas of material is there's a natural
sense in which there's a particular rest
frame the rest frame is the frame in
which on the average the molecules have
zero velocity if you're in that
reference frame then first of all light
has the same velocity that way as that
way number one and it has a velocity
that's determined by the properties of
the fluid that the sound is moving
in okay Maxwell more or less thought
that light was the same kind of thing
that there was a material and the
material had a rest frame and that
particular rest frame was the frame in
which light would moved with the same
velocity to the left as to the
right and he thought that he was working
out
the mechanics or the behavior of this
particular
material and that we were pretty much at
rest relative to this material and
that's why we saw light moving the same
way to the left or the
right one would have to say then that
Maxwell did not believe that his
equations were a universal set of laws
of
physics but that they would change when
you moved from frame to frame just
happened by some luck we happen to be
more or less at rest relative to The
Ether to this strange
material
um of course you could do an experiment
with
sound if you're moving through the sound
you can check that the Velocity in
different directions is different you do
let's not worry exactly how you do that
that's what the Michaelson Mor
experiment was Michaelson and Morley I
suppose said look the Earth is going
around in an orbit maybe at one season
of the year we just happen to be at rest
relative to The Ether by accident and
some other season 6 months later we're
going to be moving in the opposite
direction and we won't well we won't be
at rest only at one point in the orbit
could we be at rest relative to The
Ether so at any other point in the orbit
we wouldn't be
so if we measure in November that light
moves the same in all possible
directions then in um what's what's the
opposite of November may may then in may
we should find that light is moving with
a great with different velocities in
different directions and he tried it and
a very fancy and sophisticated way of
measuring the relative velocity in
different directions but he found that
there was no discrepancy that the light
traveled the same velocity in every
direction at every time of
year
uh there were all sorts of ways to try
to rescue The Ether but none of them
worked none of them worked and the
result
was one had to somehow get into the
heart of space and time and velocity and
distance and all those things in a much
deeper way in a way that didn't involve
the idea of a material at rest in some
frame of reference that uh that
propagated the
light okay uh where are we
um I forgotten where we were when we
stopped somebody remind
me who what's Omega ah Omega yeah what
is
Omega forgot I don't remember
Omega how how Omega is related not to
the speed of light but to the velocity
of the moving reference frame here we
have two reference frames XT and X Prime
and T Prime what's the relationship
between them well the whole goal here
was to understand the relationship
between frames of reference moving with
relative velocity between
them
Omega is not exactly the relative
velocity but it is closely related to
it okay let's
let's see if we can work out the
relationship we know enough to do it
relationship between
Omega and the velocity of the moving
frame all
right again let's go back to this
picture here's a frame of reference
moving
let's redraw
it here's my origin moving
along okay what does it mean to say that
from your perspective my frame of
reference or my origin is moving with
velocity V well by definition this is
not a law now this is a definition it
says that this line here has the
equation x =
VT that's the definition of this V here
my origin moves relative to your origin
it moves with a uniform constant
velocity that's an assumption that we're
talking about two inertial frames of
reference and you in your frame of
reference will write xal VT that's the
definition of v if you like what will I
call it I will call it X Prime equal 0
all along there I will say x Prime is
equal to zero it's my origin of
coordinates okay now let's
come to
this transformation law here and see if
we can spot how to identify
V
well X Prime equal 0 that's this
trajectory moving at an angle with a
velocity v x Prime equal 0 is the same
as saying
x c
Omega equals T cin
Omega X Prime equal 0 set this side
equal to zero and that says that X cos
Omega equal T cinch Omega right so
whatever the connection between velocity
and Omega is it must be such that when X
Prime is is equal to 0 x cos Omega = T C
Omega well let's look at that equation
It also says that X is equal to cinch
Omega over K
Omega time
T well that's
interesting because it's also supposed
to be equivalent to xal VT
now I know exactly how to identify what
the velocity is as a function of
Omega the velocity of the moving
transformation the moving coordinate
system must just be cinch Omega over K
Omega that's the only way these two
equations can be the same X = VT xal C
Omega over cos Omega time T so now we
know it we know what the relationship
between velocity and Omega is
write it
down the velocity of the moving frame
now this is not the velocity of light
it's just the velocity of the moving
frame must just be cinch
Omega over K
Omega well actually I want to invert
this relationship I want to find CCH and
Kos Omega in terms of the Velocity I
want to rewrite these laoren
transformations where are they I want to
rewrite these Loren
transformations in terms of the Velocity
that's the familiar form in which you
learn about it in uh in elementary
relativity books X Prime is equal to
something with velocities in it to
exhibit that all we have to do is to
find cinch and Kosh Omega in terms of
the
Velocity that's not very hard Let's uh
let's work it out the first step is to
square
it and to write v^2 is equal to S Omega
SAR over K Omega s that was
easy
next I'm going to get rid of CCH Omega
squar and substitute where is it I lost
it
uh 1 is equal to cos Omega 2 minus cinch
Omega
s all right so wherever I see cinch
Omega squar I can substitute from here
namely cos^2 omegaus 1 is equal to sin
squ
Omega so here we are this is just equal
to COS of Omega
s -1 / COS of Omega
squ
or let's multiply by what I want to do
is solve for Kos Omega in terms of
velocity I want to get rid of all these
koses and CES of Omega and rewrite it in
terms of velocity so first multiply by
cos
Omega
squared we have cos^2
omega * V ^ 2 = cos^2
Omega -
or it looks to me like this is
cos s Omega * 1 -
v^2 =
1 what I've done is
transpose yeah
cos 2 * v^ 2us cos 2
itself that gives you cos^2 1 -
v^2 = 1 change the sign can everybody
see that the second line follows from
the
first I'll give you a
second
one on
right yeah yeah yeah it's clear okay
finally we get that cos
Omega is equal to 1 / 1 - V ^2 but now I
have to take the square
root C
Omega divide by 1 - v^2 and then take
the sare root and that gives you cos
Omega now we've all seen these square
roots of 1 - v^2 in relativity
formulas here's where it begins to here
we begin to see it
materializing what about cinch Omega
let's also write down cinch
Omega well from here we see that cinch
Omega is just equal to V * cos Omega
this is easy cin Omega equal V * cos
Omega
so cinch Omega is
V / < TK of 1 -
v^2 let's go back to these Loren
Transformations over here and write them
getting rid of the trigonometric
functions the hyperbolic trigonometric
functions and substituting good old
familiar
velocities let's get rid of
this and substitute the good
old ordinary
velocities okay so we have here x Prime
= x * K Omega and that's / < TK of 1 - V
^2 then there's minus
t * cinch Omega which is V over the < TK
1 - V ^
2 or if I put the two of them together
and combine them over the same
denominator
it's just x -
VT / Square Ro
T of 1us V
^2 I think most of you have probably
seen that
before maybe slightly
different Let's uh let's clean it up a
little bit X Prime = x -
VT / theare otk of 1 - V ^
2 what about t Prime T
Prime is equal to
T minus
VX over < TK 1 - V ^
2 T Prime is equal to T * Kosh Kosh is
just 1 / square root and then x * cinch
that gives us the extra V in other words
the formulas are more or less
symmetrical and those are our good old
Loren Transformations now what's missing
is the speed of
light let's put back the speed of light
to put back the speed of light is an
exercise in dimensional
analysis there's only one possible way
the speed of light can fit into these
equations they have to be modified so
that they're dimensionally
correct first of all one is
dimensionless has no Dimensions there
just one velocity is not dimensionless
unless of course we use dimensionless uh
notation for it but if velocity is
measured in meters per second then it's
not dimensionless how do we make v²
dimensionless we divide it by the square
of the speed of light in other words
this v² which is here which has been
defined in units in which the speed of
light is one has to be replaced by these
2 over
c^2 likewise over
here V ^2 over c^2 now velocity time
time does have no notice first of all
the left hand side has units of
length the right hand side this is
dimensionless X has units of length but
so does velocity times
time so this is okay this is
dimensionally consistent as it is but
over here it's not the left hand side
has dimensions of time that's all right
1 - v^2 over c^2 that's
dimensionless this has units of time but
what about velocity time x velocity time
x does not have units of time in order
to give it units of time you have to
divide it by
c^2 okay let's check that velocity is
length over
time times length
divided by c^ SAR that's length squar oh
it's it's
correct it's
correct all right this is probably
familiar to most of you who seen
relativity once or twice before these
are the equations relating uh two
different moving coordinate systems
moving relative to the
x-axis but you see the Deep mathematics
or the ma matical structure of
it in many ways is best reflected by
this kind of hyperbolic geometry
here and uh you know most physicists by
now never write down
the Lorent transformations in this form
much more likely to write them in this
form easier to
manipulate uh easier to use trigonometry
or
um or hyperbolic
trigonometry it's a little exercise it's
a nice little exercise to
use this the hyperbolic trigonometry to
compute their to compute the compounding
of tance
Transformations if frame two is moving
relative to frame one with velocity V
and frame 3 is moving relative to two
with velocity V Prime how is three
moving relative to one
the answer is very simple in terms of
hyperbolic angles you add the hyperbolic
angles not the velocities but the
hyperbolic angles the hyperbolic angle
of three moving relative to one is the
hyperbolic angle of three moving
relative to two plus two moving relative
to one and then you use a bit of
trigonometry or or hyperbolic
trigonometry to figure out how you do
the
cinches and CES of the sum of two
hyperbolic angles very straightforward
and I'll leave it as an exercise to see
if you can work that out much easier
than anything
else okay so there there we
have the lorence
[Applause]
Transformations
an yeah oh oh absolutely yes yes that's
a that's that's a good point yeah when
we that's
right if we
have frame one let's call this X1 and y1
X2 and
Y2 and finally
X3 and
Y3 well then the
angle of two let's call it of of three
relative to 1 let's call it Theta 1
3 is just equal to Theta 1 2 + Theta 2
3 the angle connecting frame one with
frame three is just the sum of the angle
Theta 1 2 plus Theta 2
3 so in that respect the lorence
Transformations are much simpler in
terms of the
omegas it's the omegas where
um combine together to add when you add
velocities now how different is Omega
from the velocity let's work in units in
which uh the speed of light is equal to
one where is our formula for
velocity all right let's take this
formula over
here uh
what is cinch Omega for small
Omega let's put the C Square
there ah let's not put the C Square
there not put the C Square
there CCH Omega is essentially Omega
when Omega is small just like s is Omega
uh is Theta when Theta is
small the Cinch
function the cost function looks like um
like this the Cinch function looks like
this but it but it crosses the
axis with a slope of
one for small Omega cinch Omega is
proportional to Omega for small velocity
1 - v^2 is very close to 1 if the
velocity is a 100th of the speed of
light then this to within 11 10,000th is
just one
if we're talking about velocities a
millionth of the speed of light then
this is very close to one and so cinch
Omega and velocity are very close to
each other let see what's going on
[Applause]
here
thanks okay so for small velocities
Omega and velocity are the same
the actual correct statement is that V
over C is like Omega the dimensionless
velocity over the speed of light is like
Omega for small Omega and small velocity
so for small velocity adding velocities
and adding omegas are the same things
but when the velocities get large the
right way to combine them to find
relationships between different frames
is by adding Omega and not adding
velocities you when you add Omega like
compounding velocities as you've got up
there I guess you you won't go greater
than 45° I guess because that would be
faster than light no no but Omega no no
you
see the speed the speed of light is V
equals 1 yeah that corresponds to Omega
equals
infinity yeah yeah so Omega Omega runs
over the whole range from minus infinity
to Infinity but when it does v goes
from uh minus the speed of light to the
speed of light so you can add any omegas
and it's still add any omegas Omega
that's right there's no there's no speed
limit on
Omega it's just like when you're draw on
that diagram it looks like it's greater
than 45° up there where where the Omega
I guess Omega is the distance along the
hypera yeah that's right sorry we're all
right there I guess that's Theta though
isn't it this Isa
that's right
right yeah Omega is the distance along
the hyperbola that's right distance
that's right Omega
is a kind of distance along the
hyperbola all right now let's uh let's
talk about that a little
bit all right now that we've established
the basic mathematical structure of the
transformations
I think we should go back and talk about
some simple relativity
phenomena and derive
them oh one thing which is important
which I
uh yeah well let's see where here are my
larence Transformations over here I said
we we ought to at the end make sure that
our Transformations are not too
dissimilar from Newton's in particular
when the velocities are small they
should reduce to Newton that's all we
really know that's or at least that's
all that Newton really had a right to
assume that when the velocities are
smaller than something or other that his
equation should be good approximations
isn't adding velocities good enough H
isn't velocities adding good enough in
fact you're
right in fact you're right but let's
just look at the Transformations
themselves right
as long as the velocity is a small
percentage of the speed of light and
ordinary velocities are what 100 Mil an
hour versus 186,000 mil hour what is
that
uh
uh it's small right and it's doubly
small when you square
it so for typical ordinary velocities
even the velocities of the Earth around
the Sun and so forth fairly large
velocities what 60 kilometers per second
or something like that 60 kilometers per
second is pretty fast that's the that's
the orbital Earth around the Sun it's
pretty fast but it's nowhere as near
300,000 km per
no yeah 300,000 MERS per second wait uh
sorry 3 * 10 8 No 3 * 300,000
km/s right 60 k km/s 300,000 km/s small
fraction and then Square it so for
ordinary motions this is so close to one
that the deviation from one is
negligible so let's start with the top
equation for the top equation this is
negligible and it's just X Prime = x -
VT the bottom equation
here you have a c^ s in the denominator
whenever you have a c^ squ in the
denominator that's a very very large
thing in the denominator
this is
negligible compared to T so here the
speed of light is also in the
denominator just forget this and it's
just T but it's just T Prime equals T
it's just T Prime equals T so in fact
Newton's formulas are essentially
correct for slow velocities no uh no
significant departure from Newton until
the velocities get up to be some some
appreciable fraction of the speed of
light
okay uh let's talk about proper
time proper time and then let's uh do a
couple of uh relativity
examples Yeah
question in that bottom equation T Prime
when X is very large would you get
a that's right when X is exceedingly
large you get a correction but that
correction that X has to be very large
look Let's uh let's discuss before we do
anything else let's let's uh let's talk
about that a little bit x-
VT uh 1 - V ^ 2 over
c^2 yeah let's
all right in my drawings I'm going to
set c equal to
1 but in the equations you can leave the
C
there okay this equation we understand
apart from this 1 - v^2 over C2 in the
denominator it's just this x = VT or x -
vxus uh x - VT that's Newton let's look
at this one over here
okay let's look at the
surface T Prime equal
0 t Prime equal
0 is the set of points that I in my
moving reference frame call T call time
equals
z it's what I call the set of points
which are all simultane
with the
origin T Prime equal 0 is just every
place in space time which has exactly
the same time according to my frame of
reference and I will therefore call all
those points
synchronous at the same time what do you
say about them if T Prime is equal to
zero that says that t
is equal to v/
c^2 X now let's set c equal to one for
the purpose of
drawing just for the purpose of drawing
I don't want this huge number c squ to
uh to distort my drawings too much it
says that tals VX what does the surface
tals VX look like it looks like
this t
=
VX which is also X is equal to 1/
VT so it's just a
uniform line like
that all of these points are at
different times from your Reckoning this
one's later this one's later this one's
later and so forth according to my
Reckoning all these points are at the
same time so we disag age about what's
simultaneous this was this was the
hang-up incidentally this was the basic
hang-up that took so long to overcome
that took Einstein to overcome it the
idea that simultaneity was the same in
every reference frame nobody in fact it
was so obvious that nobody even thought
to ask the question is simultaneous does
it mean the same thing in every
reference frame no it doesn't in in your
reference frame the horizontal points
are all simultaneous with respect to
each other in my reference frame what I
call horizontal what I call simultaneous
you do
not okay so simultaneity had to
go let me point out one more thing about
these equations I'm not going to solve
them for you but I will tell you the
solution
anyway how do you solve for and T in
terms of X Prime and T
Prime
well think about it in the case of
angles supposing I have a relationship
like X Prime is equal to X cine Theta
what is it plus uh plus y sin Theta and
Y Prime is equal to
um uh x - x sin theta plus y cosine
Theta and supposing I want to solve for
x and y in terms of X Prime and Y Prime
you know what the solution
is just change Theta to minus Theta and
write that
X is equal to X
Prime cosine of minus Theta but what's
cosine of minus
Theta right right cosine
theta plus y sin of minus Theta what's s
ofus
Theta minus sin
Theta *
Y and likewise for y Prime y Prime is
equal to - x * sin of minus Theta so
that becomes +
x sin
Theta + y cosine of minus Theta which is
cosine
Theta you don't have to go through the
the business of solving the equations
you know that if one set of axes is
related to the other by Rotation by
angle Theta the second one is related to
the first one or vice versa the first
one is related to the second one by the
negative of the angle if to go from one
frame to another you rotate by angle
Theta then to go from the second frame
back to the first you rotate by angle
minus Theta so you just write down
exactly the same equations interchange
Prime and unprimed and substitute for
Theta minus Theta same thing for the
Lorent
Transformations exactly the same thing
if you want to solve these for x and t
write down the same equations replace
primed by unprimed and change the sign
of omegas to minus the signs of omegas
change the sinus I GN of all the sign
all the
cches okay in other words just send
Omega to minus
Omega and that will solve the equations
in the other direction
yeah yes it's also the same as changing
V to minus
V yes the way to see
that is to
go
right uh what was it what did we have C
Omega
yep y That's Right V is
sign yes that was correct yeah you just
when you change Omega to minus Omega it
has the action of changing V to minus V
you can just check that from the
equations good all right let's uh let's
talk about proper time a little
bit proper time
if you're doing ordinary
geometry you can measure the length
along a curve for
example and the way you do it is you
take a tape measure and you uh you know
you sort of tick off you tick off equal
intervals equal uh equal little
separations you can think of these
separations as differential distances DS
s small little different differential
distances and that differential distance
is dx2 + D
y^2 well the x^2 and the y^2 are just
the uh the differential increments in X
and Y DX and Dy this is
DS all right so that's the way and you
add them up you add them up that's the
way you compute distances along curves
it's quite obvious that if you take two
points the distance between those two
points depends on what
curve not the same for every curve so
measured along a curve you have to know
not only the two points but you have to
know the curve in order to say what the
distance between those points are of
course the distance between along a
straight line that's that's well defined
but the distance along a curve depends
on the curve in any case DS2 = DX s + D
y^2 is the basic
defining um notion of distance between
two neighboring points if you know the
distance between any two neighboring
points in a geometry you basically know
that geometry almost essentially
completely so given this formula for the
distance between two points you can
compute if you like the distance along a
curve course you've got to take the
square root of this and then add them up
don't add don't add the squares add the
differential distances all right the
important thing is here that square root
of dx2 + D y^2 which is the distance
between neighboring points doesn't
depend on your choice of axes I could
choose XY AIS I could choose X Prime y
Prime
axis if I take a little differential
displacement the X and Dy or I just take
two points two neighboring points don't
even give them labels
and measure the distance between them
the distance between them should not
depend on conventions such as which axes
I use and so when I make rotational
Transformations the x^2 + D y^2 doesn't
change thex and the Y may change but the
X S Plus the Y sare does not change the
same thing is
true in relativity or the analogous
thing we don't measure distances along
the paths of particles let's say now
that this curve here is the path of a
particle moving through
SpaceTime there's a particle moving
through space
time and we want some notion of the
distance along
it the notion of distance along
it another example would just be a
particle standing still as a particle
standing
still particle standing still is still
in some sense moving in
time I wouldn't want to say that the the
distance between these two points in
space time is zero they're not the same
point I wouldn't like to say it's zero I
would like to say there's some kind of
notion of distance between them but it's
quite clear that that distance is not
measured with a tape
measure this point and this point are
the same point of space boom here at
this point of space and then at a later
time boom again at the same point of
space two events at the same point of
space how do I characterize in some nice
way the
distance between those two events that
occurred in the same place you don't do
it with a tape measure all right what do
you do it with a clock a clock you take
a clock and you start it at this point
tick tick tick tick tick tick tick and a
stopwatch you press it at this point
tick tick tick tick tick it kcks off
intervals and then you stop it at that
point and you see how much time has
evolved that's a notion of distance
along a particle trajectory it's not the
distance the particle Moves In Space
it's a kind of distance that it's moved
through SpaceTime and it's not not zero
even if the particle is moving standing
perfectly still in fact what it is is
it's the time along the trajectory what
about a moving particle well you can
imagine that a moving particle carries a
clock with it of course not all
particles carry clocks but we can
imagine they carry clocks with them as
they move and we can start the clock
over here and end the clock over
here what is the time read off by this
moving clock the time read off by a
moving clock is much like the distance
along a
curve measured by a tape measure in
particular it should not depend on the
choice of
coordinates why not this is a question
that has nothing to do with coordinates
I have a clock made in the standard
clock Factory the standard clock Factory
in uh I don't know where in Switzerland
someplace makes a certain kind of clock
that clock gets carried along with a
particle and we ask how much time
evolves or how much time
elapses or how much the clock changes
between here and here that should not
depend on a choice of
coordinates it shouldn't depend on a
choice of coordinates because it's a
physical question that only involves
looking at the hands of the clock in
fact we could ask it for little
intervals along uh along the trajectory
we could ask how much time elapses
according to the clock between here and
here well the answer again should not
depend on what coordinates you use which
lorence frame you use and there's only
one invariant quantity that you can make
out of the DXs and DTS describing this
point describing these two
points there's a little interval DT and
there's a little interval
DX now we're in space and time not
ordinary not ordinary
space and the quantity which is
invariant is really only one invariant
quantity that you can make out of it it
is dt^
2 minus DX
s it's the same
quantity x^2 - t s for a whole uh you
know for a whole
interval DT ^2 minus
dx2 that's the quantity which is
invariant it's minus the it's it's the
negative of what I wrote over here x^2 -
t^2 okay this
quantity is equal to DX Prime s minus DT
uh sorry DT Prime s minus the X Prime
squ the same algebra goes into this as
goes into showing that X Prime 2 - t
Prime 2 = x^2 - t^2 incidentally this is
the same as saying T Prime 2 - x Prime 2
= T ^2 -
x^2 doesn't matter which way you write
it all right so that suggests that
suggests that the time time read off the
invariant time read off along a
trajectory between two points separated
by DX and DT is just the square root of
dt^ 2 minus dx^
2 why the square root
incidentally well okay you're going to
integrate it detal well I can integrate
y well all right why not just the t^2
minus the x^2 for the time between here
and here here's here's an answer
supposing we go two you two intervals
exactly the same as the first one we go
an interval over here DX and DT and then
we go another DX and
DT what happens when we double the
interval to DT ^2 minus the
x^2 it gets multiplied by four because
everything is squared well I wouldn't
expect a clock when it goes along you
know when it goes along a trajectory for
twice the uh the interval here to
measure four times the uh the time I
expect it to measure twice the time so
for that reason the square root is the
appropriate thing here okay that's
called D Squared the to
squared the proper time along the
trajectory of an object
that's just you're right that's just
D or D squ being dx^ 2 minus d t ^2 the
tow is called the proper
time
it's I think we'll let's
see the tow is called the proper time
and it is the time read by a clock
moving along a trajectory it's not just
detail
that's the important thing it's not just
DT DT ^2 minus
dx2 uh let's do one last thing let's
just do the twin paradox in this
language I think I think I've had it I'm
going to
finish uh you can do the twin paradox in
this
language all you have to do is to
compute the proper time along two
trajectories one one that goes out with
a uniform velocity turns around and
comes back with the same uniform
velocity versus a trajectory which just
goes from one point to the same to
another point along a straight line and
it's no
more weird it's no weirder really from
this perspective than saying the
distance from one point to another along
two different curves
do not have to
agree the proper time along two
different Curves in general will not
agree what is a little bit weird is that
because of this minus sign the proper
time this way is less than the proper
time this way that's the consequence of
this minus sign
here moving with some
DX decreases the proper time all right
we'll do a little a little bit more next
time but then I want to get to the
principles of field Theory and uh
and connect some of this with field
equations for interesting wave
[Music]
Fields the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu